Guide to the Chlingensperg Family Diaries
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Chlingensperg family diaries
1769-1830
GEN MSS 1495
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.25
(3 boxes)
The Chlingensperg Family Diaries, which span from 1769 to 1830, contain diaries kept by four members of a prominent Bavarian family: Joseph Maria Bernhard von Chlingensperg, Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg, Karoline von Chlingensperg, and Joseph von Chlingensperg. The subject matter of the entries ranges from financial and professional records to details of the sexual affairs of Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg.
Chlingensperg family
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Jonathan A. Hill, Bookseller Inc. on the Henny and Rudolf Engelbarts Fund, 2018.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Joseph Maria Bernhard von Chlingensperg diaries, 1769-1778. II. Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg diaries, 1801-1830. III. Karoline von Chlingensperg diaries, 1823-1825.
Chlingensperg Family
Joseph Maria Bernhard von Chlingensperg (1749-1811) was Lord of Schönhofen near Regensburg and of Berg near Landshut. He was involved in the legal profession in Bavaria and served as privy councilor to the Bavarian Elector in Munich.
Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg (1777-1830) was the son of Joseph Maria Bernhard von Chlingensperg. He was involved in the legal profession and served as a courtroom councillor under the King of Bavaria.
Karoline von Chlingensperg (1789-1826), born Baroness von Asch, was the wife of Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg. She married Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg on 13 August, 1806. She managed the Chlingensperg household.
Joseph von Chlingensperg (1808-1837) was the son of Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg (1777-1830).
Scope and Contents
The Chlingensperg Family Diaries, which span from 1769 to 1830, contain diaries kept by four members of a prominent Bavarian family: Joseph Maria Bernhard von Chlingensperg, Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg, Karoline von Chlingensperg, and Joseph von Chlingensperg. The subject matter of the entries ranges from financial and professional records to details of the sexual affairs of Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg.
The diaries are written in annual editions of a Schreib-Kalender printed in Munich.
Entries from 1805 through 1830 authored by Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg are encrypted with cipher of his own construction. Some passages have been decoded into German in notes laid in through select volumes. The 1811 volume has been decoded in full in a 33-page manuscript included in the collection.
Diaries; Bavaria (Germany)
- Joseph Maria Bernhard von Chlingensperg diaries, 1769-1778; Series I; 1; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Entries concern Joseph Maria Bernhard von Chlingensperg's professional life, financial matters, and occasionally daily activities.
  - Diary, 1769 (Box 1)
    1 loose leaf of paper laid in front of book. Leaf appears to be from a time period after the diaries from 1769-1778 were completed and may have originally been affixed to the cover by an adhesive.
  - Diary, 1770 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1771 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1772 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1773 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1774 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1775 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1776 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1777 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1778 (Box 1)
- Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg diaries, 1801-1830; Series II; 2; (2 boxes + 7 folders)
  Entries concern Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg's professional and financial matters, as well as his active sex life. The diary from 1804 is not present in the collection, and the diary from 1805 has large sections of the volume cut out.
  Entries from 1805 through 1830 are encrypted with cipher of Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg's own construction. The cipher has since been cracked by multiple sources. In addition to his cipher, he indicated an instance of sexual intercourse with an oval drawn on the calendar date; the number of dashes through the oval indicated the number of orgasms.
  - Diary, 1801 (Box 1)
    Laid in at the front of the volume are two sheets about the decoding of Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg's cipher, along with a makeshift envelope, contemporary, that contains a letter from "Therese" (two bifolia and a single leaf) addressed to Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg.
    Laid in throughout are notes (not contemporary).
  - Diary, 1802 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1803 (Box 1)
    Schrieb-kalender used for this diary is from a different printer than the Schrieb-Kalenders used for all other diaries in the collection; a page is provided for every month instead of for every week.
    Diary does not contain entries from April through December (pages are present, but blank).
  - Encrypted diary, 1805 (Box 1)
    Laid in at front of volume are notes on cipher translation from multiple sources: a contemporary source (likely Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg's son, Joseph von Chlingensperg), a 20th century owner, and possibly Jonathan Hill.
    A number of pages appear to have been cut out from the volume entirely; the first printed date that appears is the week of August 18th. Parts of other pages also appear to have been cut out.
  - Encrypted diary, 1806 (Box 1)
    While it is the same Schrieb-Kalender as every other volume (except 1803), this volume is in a paperback binding.
    Notes from contemporary and later sources are laid in throughout, some with decoded passages of the diary.
  - Encrypted diary, 1807 (Box 1)
    Notes from a later source are laid in throughout with decoded passages of the diary.
  - Encrypted diary, 1808 (Box 1)
  - Encrypted diary, 1809 (Box 2)
  - Encrypted diary, 1810 (Box 2)
  - Encrypted diary, 1811 (Box 2)
  - Translation of 1811 diary, with related papers, 20th century (Box 2)
    Includes a complete 33-page printed cipher translation for the 1811 volume (with an additional 2 page index) and 8 loose leaves of notes.
  - Encrypted diary, 1812 (Box 2)
  - Encrypted diary, 1813 (Box 2)
  - Encrypted diary, 1814 (Box 2)
  - Encrypted diary, 1815 (Box 2)
  - Encrypted diary, 1816 (Box 2)
  - Encrypted diary, 1817 (Box 2)
  - Encrypted diary, 1818 (Box 2)
  - Encrypted diary, 1819 (Box 2)
  - Encrypted diary, 1820 (Box 2)
  - Encrypted diary, 1821 (Box 2)
  - Encrypted diary, 1822 (Box 2)
  - Encrypted diary, 1823 (Box 3)
    Several loose leaves of paper that appear to be contemporary are laid in at the front of the volume.
  - Encrypted diary, 1824 (Box 3)
  - Encrypted diary, 1825 (Box 3)
    This volume is encrypted with a cipher created by Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg.
  - Encrypted diary, 1826 (Box 3)
  - Encrypted diary, 1827 (Box 3)
  - Encrypted diary, 1828 (Box 3)
  - Encrypted diary, 1829 (Box 3)
  - Partially encrypted diary, 1830 (Box 3)
    This volume is partially encrypted with a cipher created by Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg.
    Entries prior to May 5th were written by Joseph von Chlingensperg auf Berg and encrypted in his cipher. Entries from May 23rd through the end of the volume were written by his son, Joseph von Chlingensperg, in German.
- Karoline von Chlingensperg diaries, 1823-1825; Series III; 3
  Entries concern household management, including lists of items purchased, salaries of domestic workers, and expenditure totals for each month and year.
  - Diary, 1823 (Box 3)
  - Diary, 1824 (Box 3)
  - Diary, 1825 (Box 3)